SHEIKH AHMED

New York, NY | 347-933-8355 | ssahme21@gmail.com |linkedin.com/in/sheikhahmed21/ | github.com/ArcRiseGen132

FRONTEND ENGINEER & APPLICATION DEVELOPER

"Developing Innovative Solutions to Empower Existing Systems through Creative Software Development & Programming." Intellectually curious and solutions-focused professional with almost 10 years of diversified experience in driving innovation through software development (primarily in Javascript, HTML, CSS) and education. Expert in managing system, network, and application-related projects. A multifaceted IT professional with unmatched leadership and astute technical acumen to drive operational excellence through strategic full-stack development in MERN (Mongo, Express, React, Node) and cybersecurity. Passionate at being at the forefront of change to maximize resources, address client business issues, and promote organizational growth.

TECHNICAL EXPERTISE

- MERN Stack

- Node.js
- NoSQL

- MongoDB
- Javascript
- NPM/Yarn
- **Express**
- HTML 5
- Visual Studio Code
- React.is
- CSS/Bootstrap
- Git/Github

CORE COMPETENCIES

- **Technical Planning & Analysis**
- Software Development
- **Object-Oriented Programming**
- Software Testing & Debugging
- Cross-Functional Project Management •
- Troubleshooting & Conflict Resolution •
- Technical Documentation & Reporting •
- Scrum & Agile Methodologies
- **Team Collaboration & Coordination**
- **Technical Support & Client Relations**
- Team Leadership & Initiative
- Quality Assurance & Quality Control

SOFTWARE DEVELOPMENT PROJECTS

Cryptocurrency Value Tracking

August 2022

Connected application to CoinGecko API and retrieved the values of top 100 cryptocurrencies by using Axios, rendering data onto the page, creating a search function to take user input, and fetching cryptocurrency data based on the input field value.

GameStart (Capstone Project)

October 2021

Recognized as the Scrum Master of the team, accountable for communicating the project progress across team members from different time zones, supporting the frontend development to alleviate password verifications and data storage issues. Co-coded a website using MERN Stack and MongoDB servers, allowing users to browse through various games, add to purchases, create user accounts, display purchases, and comment on game pages.

Kenzie Snippets Application

July 2021

Identified and alleviated technical bugs for a mock social media website project, such as infinite rendering, local storage not saving login sessions, adjusting backend routing, adding password verification using bcrypt, and creating a search function based on user post content, resulting in smoother user experiences. Coded in MERN Stack to debug version conflicts and custom hooks while working with legacy code to update to newer standards.

Kenzie Hardware Store Website

June 2021

Developed basic shopping pages with user functionality, using various React hooks to prevent rendering issues, keep persistent shopping cart states, and pass data between components.

RELEVANT PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Recognized as the strategic coach, developing effective curriculum content and instructing fundamental principles and best practices of programming to 300+ cohort students and learners of cybersecurity, HTML, CSS, and JavaScript.

- Exhibit excellent written and verbal communication skills to assist learners with their projects and assignments, complete instructional reports, manage study hall sessions and respond to various student inquiries.
- Strategically enhance and debug the curriculum content in Canvas for testing assignments before release, allowing for a better user experience for incoming students.
- Respond and complete over 50 ticket requests regarding technical issues, grading, and extension requests.

Field Service Technician, FREELANCE, New York City, NY

June 2018 - December 2020

Singlehandedly troubleshot, repaired, upgraded, and addressed technical issues on hardware, software, operating systems, and network connections as requested by clients.

- Focused on customer needs and satisfaction in performing various technical services and providing quick-paced solutions.
- Demonstrated excellent time management skills in handling multiple projects, customer support, and technical requests.

IT Support, SMART ACADEMIA, New York City, NY

October 2012 – May 2018

Spearheaded the school's computer maintenance and system upgrade, including software troubleshooting, equipment repair, network security, application installation, and inventory control.

- Oversaw the daily performance of computer systems, performing minor repairs to hardware, software, and peripheral equipment, following design or system installation specifications.
- Managed data communication issues, consulting with users and management to identify needs for system modifications.

OTHER WORK EXPERIENCE

Private Tutor, FREELANCE, New York City, NY
Lead Tutor, SMART ACADEMIA, New York City, NY

August 2018 – Present October 2012 – May 2018

CERTIFICATES & PROFESSIONAL DEVELOPMENT

CYBERSECURITY AWARENESS: BUILDING YOUR CYBERSECURITY VOCABULARY – LinkedIn	April 2022
CYBERSECURITY AWARENESS: MALWARE EXPLAINED— LinkedIn	April 2022
CYBERSECURITY AWARENESS: THE INTERNET OF THINGS (IOT) – LinkedIn	April 2022
SQL ESSENTIAL TRAINING – LinkedIn	April 2022
COMPTIA A+ – CompTIA	September 2020
COMPTIA SECURITY+ – CompTIA	September 2020

EDUCATION

FULL-STACK SOFTWARE ENGINEERING (MERN) – Kenzie Academy, Indianapolis, IN

BACHELOR OF ARTS IN MASS COMMUNICATION/MEDIA STUDIES – Hunter College, New York City, NY

October 2021 January 2016